<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Questions and Answers</title>

  <para>We advice you to read also the user documentation - especially the
  tricks, tips &#38; tools - chapter.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>General</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is SUMO?</title>

      <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>What is SUMO?</para>

      <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> SUMO is a traffic simulation package.
      It is meant to be used to simulate networks of a city&#39;s size, but
      you can of course use it for smaller networks and larger, too, if your
      computer power is large enough.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What does &#34;SUMO&#34; mean?</title>

      <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>What does &#34;SUMO&#34; mean?</para>

      <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> &#34;SUMO&#34; is an acronym for
      &#34;Simulation of Urban MObility&#34;.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What kind of a traffic simulation is SUMO?</title>

      <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>What kind of a traffic simulation
      is SUMO?</para>

      <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> SUMO is a microscopic,
      space-continuous road traffic simulation. In the next time it will be
      extended to be multi-modal.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Building</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Getting the sources</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>How do I access the CVS using cygwin or Linux?</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>How do I access the CVS?</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Use the following commands:</para>

        <para><command>export CVS_RSH=ssh</command></para>

        <para><command>cvs -z3
        -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/sumo co sumo</command></para>

        <para>Press RETURN if you should be asked for a password.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Is there further documentation on the CVS?</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>Is there further documentation on
        the CVS?</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Look under <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/docman/?group_id=1">Sourceforge
        documentation</ulink> in Section F.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Windows and MSVC++</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>moc-files not found</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>For the GUI project I didn’t find
        files such as &#34;moc_GUIApplicationWindow.cpp&#34; (there are seven
        files beginning with “moc_” ). If I delete them, I have some link
        errors like : error LNK2001: unresolved external symbol
        &#34;protected: virtual void __thiscall
        GUIApplicationWindow::initMetaObject(void)&#34;
        (?initMetaObject@GUIApplicationWindow@@MAEXXZ)</para>

        <para>Do you have any suggestions to resolve this problem ?</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Yes, those files are used by the
        Qt-library (www.troll-tech.com) and are build automatically. If you
        take a look into the project settings (MSVC++:
        project-&#62;settings-&#62;gui) and open the file browser within this
        window, some .h-files have another icon. If you click on one of these
        and choose the &#34;user defined building&#34; (I do not exactly know
        how it is called in english), you will see some additional program
        calls.</para>

        <para>To build the gui, you have to install Qt2.3 which includes some
        additional programs within a bin-folder, automatically installed. Set
        the environment variable &#34;QTDIR&#34; to the folder you have
        installed Qt into (not to the bin-folder as you may see from the calls
        within the project). This should let MSVC++ build the moc*-files
        first.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Features</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Traffic within junctions</title>

      <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>Does SUMO support traffic within
      the junctions?</para>

      <para>No, not yet. There is an approach towards this, but it is not yet
      in such a stable state that it would be useable.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Connection with an external application</title>

      <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>Is it possible to connect SUMO to
      an external application (f.e. ns-2)?</para>

      <para>No, not yet. We have build an internal version which handles
      connections to other applications, but it&#39;s not yet available as
      open source. So in principle, it is possible, but there is nothing that
      does it within the current code.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Errors</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Strange and cryptic Errors</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>What does the following error
        mean?</para>

        <para>Warning: No types defined, using defaults... Error: An exception
        occurred! Type:RuntimeException, Message:The primary document entity
        could not be opened. Id=&#60;PATH&#62; Error: (At line/column 1/0).
        Error: Quitting (conversion failed).</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Simply that the file you try to use
        (&#60;PATH&#62;) does not exist. This is xercec&#39; way to say
        &#34;file not found&#34;.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Netconvert</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Windows</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>The application hangs after a while (few memory consumption,
        most of the system time)</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>When I start the SUMO-NETCONVERT
        with large networks, the system hangs after a while. The program uses
        most of the system time, but when I look into the task manager almost
        no memory is used.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> You are propably running a program
        compiled in the debug-mode. This yields in at least the triple of
        normal memory usage and your system may not be able to solve. Try to
        use the normal version, build in Release-mode (or buy more RAM :-) ).</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Routing</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Random Routes</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>No random routes are generated</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>I have tried to insert vehicles
        using the -R option, but the route file is empty.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> On the one hand, SUMO-routers quit
        processing if a route could not be build. On the other hand, the
        generation of a random route may fail quite easily, simply because
        it&#39;s too short or no connection could have been found. If you have
        made everything right, but your route file is empty, try to use the
        --continue-on-unbuild switch on your command line / within your
        configuration file.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Simulation</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Networks</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Network changes</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>I have changed my network and now
        SUMO does not load it.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Actually, SUMO-networks are not
        meant to be edited by hand. You have to describe everything within the
        your input properly and let NETVCONVERT build your network. Editing
        networks by hand is very complicated and error-proned.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Vehicles</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>No vehicle appears</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>I have build the network and
        routes like described, but no vehicle can be seen)</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> We encountered this problem under
        the following circumstances: As we imported a network where the
        maximum speed allowed on was given in km/h instead of the supposed
        m/s, no vehicle could be emitted due to a too large space needed for
        oncoming traffic. Check whether your network description also defines
        speed in km/h. If so, use the SUMO-NETCONVERT - switch
        &#34;speed-in-km&#34; to recompute the speed limits. If this does not
        help, contact us.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Vehicle jumps backward</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>When I try to evaluate my vehicle
        dump, sometimes vehicle seem to jump backward (their position is
        smaller than in the previous step)</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> To avoid jams due to an
        inappropriate lane changing behaviour, vehicles may swap their lanes.
        In this case each vehicle obtains the position and speed of the other
        vehicle. As the position of the vehicles may differ a bit, one of the
        vehicles may seem to jump backwards.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Remark:</emphasis> This should not happen from
        Version0.8 on.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Visualisation</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Windows</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Display flickers in the area of the mouse pointer</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>Why is the view around the mouse
        pointer distorted?</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Newer Windows-Versions seem to
        cache the area under the mouse to apply the mouse shadow afterwards.
        To avoid this, go to your Systemmenu, then Mouse-&#62;Pointers and
        disable the mouse shadows. That&#39;s the only solution so far.
        (Origin: Till Oliver Knoll, via QT Interest List)</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>