<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<book
><bookinfo
><title
>SUMO - Simulation of Urban MObility - Projects</title
><author
><firstname
>Daniel</firstname
><surname
>Krajzewicz</surname
><affiliation
><address
><email
>Daniel.Krajzewicz@dlr.de</email
></address
></affiliation
></author
><releaseinfo
>$Revision$</releaseinfo
></bookinfo
><toc
></toc
><chapter
id="user_chp01"
><title
>Introduction</title
><sect1
><title
>What is SUMO?</title
><para
>SUMO is a traffic simulation tool. It was primarily designed for urban street networks, but it may also be used for highway traffic simulations. In the near future it will be extended to model other transit modes simultaneously with ordinary car traffic.</para
></sect1
><sect1
><title
>Why open source?</title
><para
>Two thoughts stood behind the release of the package as open source. At first the fact that every traffic research organisation has to implement an own simulation package for its own. Some people are interested in traffic light optimisation, other try to find mistakes made during the design of a road network. Both need some kind of a simulation package and have to implement a framework containing input and output functions and other things from scratch. So the first idea was to give them a basic framework - containing all needed methods for a simulation - they can put own ideas into.</para
><para
>The second idea is to supply a common test bed for models, especially car models, to the community to make them comparable. Due to different architectures of traffic simulations such comparisons on a wide scale are not possible by now.</para
></sect1
><sect1
><title
>Features</title
><para
><itemizedlist
spacing="compact"
><listitem
><para
>High portability (using standard - c++ and portable libraries only)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Collision free vehicle movement</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Different vehicle types</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Single-vehicle routing</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Multi-lane streets with lane changing</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Junction-based right-of-way rules</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Hierarchy of junction types</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>A fast openGL graphical user interface</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Dynamic routing</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Manages networks with several 10.000 edges (streets)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Fast execution speed (up to 100.000 vehicle updates/s on a 1GHz machine)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Supports import of many network formats (Visum, Vissim, ArcView, XML-Descriptions)</para
></listitem
></itemizedlist
></para
></sect1
><sect1
><title
>About this document</title
><para
>This document describes how to use each of the applications that come with the SUMO-package.</para
><para
>This document is still under development and is meant to grow with the software. Due to this, you may find it together with the sources within out repository at sourceforge (<ulink
url="http://sumo.sourceforge.net"
>http://sumo.sourceforge.net/</ulink
>). It should always describe the current version.</para
><para
>We should remark, that this document only covers the usage of the software and some description of the models used. Information about the programming side - if you want to extend the software what is really appreciated by us - may be found in the programmer manual.</para
><para
>We should also remark, that the previous division of documents where each document described a single application is now abandoned. We hope to make the process of simulation easier to understand.</para
></sect1
><sect1
><title
>Call for Help</title
><para
>Please let us know when either the document remains at any point unclear or any of the applications does not behave as expected. We also seek for some participants and further users, not only to share the development tasks, but also to gain some feedback and critics or some usage examples.</para
><para
>Every help is appreciated. Thank you.</para
></sect1
></chapter
><chapter
id="user_chp03"
><title
>T!!!O</title
><sect1
><title
>Some Traffic Simulation Theory</title
><sect2
><title
>Simulation types</title
><para
>SUMO is a microscopic, space continuous and time discrete traffic simulation.</para
><para
>In traffic research three or four classes of models are distinguished according to the level of detail of the simulation. In macroscopic models traffic flow is the basic entity. Microscopic models simulate the movement of every single vehicle on the street, mostly assuming that the behaviour of the vehicle depends on both, the vehicle&#39;s physical abilities to move and the driver&#39;s controlling behaviour (Krauss 1998; Janz 1998). Sub-microscopic models regard single vehicles like microscopic but extend them by modelling their substructures, which describe the engine&#39;s rotation speed in relation to the vehicle&#39;s speed or the driver&#39;s preferred gear switching actions, for instance. This allows more detailed computations of the emissions produced by the vehicle compared to a simple microscopic simulation (Diekamp 1995; Schreckenberg and Wolf 1998; Helbig et al. 2001). However, sub-microscopic models require large computation times. This restrains the size of the networks to be simulated.</para
><figure
><title
>The different simulation granularities; from left to right: macroscopic, microscopic, sub-microscopic (within the circle: mesoscopic)</title
><mediaobject
><imageobject
><imagedata
align="center"
fileref="./gfx/user/3sims.gif"
format="GIF"
></imagedata
></imageobject
></mediaobject
></figure
><para
>Within a space-continuous simulation each vehicle has a certain position described by a floating-point number. In contrast, space-discrete simulations are a special kind of cellular automata. They use cells and vehicles driving on the simulated streets &#34;jump&#34; from one cell to another (Brockfeld et al 2001).</para
><figure
><title
>The difference between a space-continuous (top) and a space-discrete (bottom) simulation</title
><mediaobject
><imageobject
><imagedata
align="center"
fileref="./gfx/user/contdisc.gif"
format="GIF"
></imagedata
></imageobject
></mediaobject
></figure
><para
>And there is another difference between the available simulation packages. Almost every simulation packages uses an own model for vehicle movement. Almost all models are so-called &#34;car-following-models&#34;: the behaviour of the driver is herein meant to be dependent on his distance to the vehicle in front of him and of this vehicle&#39;s speed. Although SUMO is meant to be a test bed for such vehicle models, only one is implemented by now, which was developed by Stefan Kraus. Other obstacles such as traffic lights are of course considered herein, too. Please take a look into &#34;Used models&#34; for a more detailed description of the Krauß-model.</para
></sect2
><sect2
><title
>Needed Data</title
><para
>What data is needed to simulate traffic? At first, you need the network the traffic to simulate takes place on. As SUMO is meant to work with large networks, we mainly concentrated our work on importing networks and the computation of further needed values. Beside information about a network&#39;s roads, information about traffic lights is needed.</para
><para
>Further, you need information of the traffic demand. While most traffic simulation use a statistical distribution which is laid over the network, each vehicle within SUMO knows its route. Within this approach, the route is a list of edges to pass. Although this approach is more realistic, it also induces a large amount of data needed to describe the vehicle movements. By now, routes are not compressed within SUMO and so may be several MB large. We will possibly change this in future.</para
></sect2
><sect2
><title
>User Assignment</title
><para
>It seems obvious, that each driver is trying to use to shortest path through the network. But when all are trying to do this, some of the roads - mainly the arterial roads would get congested and their benefit would sink. This problem is known to traffic research as the dynamic user assignment. Some approaches have been developed to solve this.</para
></sect2
></sect1
><sect1
><title
>The Workflow of preparing a Simulation</title
><para
>As shortly described above, you basically have to the following steps: generation of the road network and generation of the vehicle movements. After this, you can perform your first simulation steps. This process is also visualised within the next figure.</para
><para
>Please remark, that most of the tools are command-line tools by now. They do nothing if you just double-click them. Do also notice, that we describe the call parameter in the following chapters which may be also stored in so-called &#34;configuration files&#34; to allow their reuse. This possibility is described on a later place in the document.</para
><figure
><title
>Process of simulation with SUMO; (grey and rounded: data used; white: program calls)</title
><mediaobject
><imageobject
><imagedata
align="center"
fileref="./gfx/user/simsteps1.gif"
format="GIF"
scale="1"
></imagedata
></imageobject
></mediaobject
></figure
></sect1
><sect1
><title
>Main Software Paradigms</title
><para
>Two basic design goals are approached: the software shall be fast and it shall be portable. Due to this, the very first versions were developed to be run from the command line - no graphical interface was supplied at first and all parameter had to be inserted by hand. Also, due to these goals, the software was split into several parts. Each of them has a certain purpose and must be run individually. This is something that makes SUMO different to other simulation packages where the dynamical user assignment is made within the simulation itself, not via an external application like here.</para
><para
>The split allows an easier extension of the application&#39;s part as they small enough and it also allows the usage of faster data structures, each adjusted to the current purpose, instead of using complicated and ballast-loaded ones. Still, this makes the usage of SUMO a little bit uncomfortable in comparison to other simulation packages. As there are still other things to do, we are not thinking of a redesign towards an integrated approach by now.</para
></sect1
></chapter
></book
>