<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>SUMO examples documentation</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

      <surname>Krajzewicz</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <address><email>Daniel.Krajzewicz@dlr.de</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <chapter id="dev_chp01">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>What is SUMO?</title>

      <para>SUMO is a traffic simulation tool. It was primarily designed for
      urban street networks, but it may also be used for highway traffic
      simulations. In the near future it will be extended to model other
      transit modes simultaneously with ordinary car traffic.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Why open source?</title>

      <para>Two thoughts stood behind the release of the package as open
      source. At first the fact that every traffic research organisation has
      to implement an own simulation package for its own. Some people are
      interested in traffic light optimisation, other try to find mistakes
      made during the design of a road network. Both need some kind of a
      simulation package and have to implement a framework containing input
      and output functions and other things from scratch. So the first idea
      was to give them a basic framework - containing all needed methods for a
      simulation - they can put own ideas into.</para>

      <para>The second idea is to supply a common test bed for models,
      especially car models, to the community to make them comparable. Due to
      different architectures of traffic simulations such comparisons on a
      wide scale are not possible by now.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Features</title>

      <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>High portability
      (using standard - c++ and portable libraries only)</para></listitem><listitem><para>Collision
      free vehicle movement</para></listitem><listitem><para>Different vehicle
      types</para></listitem><listitem><para>Single-vehicle routing</para></listitem><listitem><para>Multi-lane
      streets with lane changing</para></listitem><listitem><para>Junction-based
      right-of-way rules</para></listitem><listitem><para>Hierarchy of
      junction types</para></listitem><listitem><para>A fast openGL graphical
      user interface</para></listitem><listitem><para>Dynamic routing</para></listitem><listitem><para>Manages
      networks with several 10.000 edges (streets)</para></listitem><listitem><para>Fast
      execution speed (up to 1.000.000 vehicle updates/s on a 1GHz machine)</para></listitem><listitem><para>Supports
      import of many network formats (Visum, Vissim, ArcView,
      XML-Descriptions)</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>About this document</title>

      <para>This document describes the examples that come with the release
      packages.</para>

      <para>This document is still under development and is meant to grow with
      the software. Due to this, you may find it together with the sources
      within out repository at sourceforge (<ulink
      url="http://sumo.sourceforge.net">http://sumo.sourceforge.net/</ulink>).
      It should always describe the current version.</para>

      <para>We should also remark, that the previous division of documents
      where each document described a single application is now abandoned. We
      hope to make the process of simulation easier to understand.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Call for Help</title>

      <para>Please let us know when either the document remains any point
      unclear or any of the application does not behave as expected. We also
      seek for some participants and further users, not only to share the
      development tasks, but also to gain some feedback and critics or some
      usage examples.</para>

      <para>Every help is appreciated. Thank you.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="dev_chp02">
    <title>Simple</title>

    <para>This chapter describes the examples that may be found in the folder
    SUMO/data/examples/simple.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>General Description</title>

      <para>The &#34;Simple Examples&#34;-Package contains three packages,
      each containing a set of variations of a certain shape. The following
      image shows how the networks within each of these packages
      (&#34;box&#34;, &#34;cross&#34;, &#34;eight&#34;) look like.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>All Platforms: Obtaining the sources</title>

        <para>There are two possibilities to obtain the sources needed to
        build SUMO. The first is to download the latest distribution, located
        within the <ulink
        url="http://sumo.sourceforge.net/downloads.html#sumo-latest">download</ulink>
        section of our <ulink url="http://sumo.sourceforge.net">internet pages</ulink>
        internet pages. The other one is to checkout the <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=45607">current CVS</ulink>
        tree (Use <literal>sumo</literal> as <literal>modulname</literal>).</para>

        <para>Normally, the CVS tree is stable and of course does contain the
        latest patches, the latest release may not contain.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>