<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Questions and Answers</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Building</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Windows and MSVC++</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>moc-files not found</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>For the GUI project I didn’t find
        files such as &#34;moc_GUIApplicationWindow.cpp&#34; (there are seven
        files beginning with “moc_” ). If I delete them, I have some link
        errors like : error LNK2001: unresolved external symbol
        &#34;protected: virtual void __thiscall
        GUIApplicationWindow::initMetaObject(void)&#34;
        (?initMetaObject@GUIApplicationWindow@@MAEXXZ)</para>

        <para>Do you have any suggestions to resolve this problem ?</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Yes, those files are used by the
        Qt-library (www.troll-tech.com) and are build automatically. If you
        take a look into the project settings (MSVC++:
        project-&#62;settings-&#62;gui) and open the file browser within this
        window, some .h-files have another icon. If you click on one of these
        and choose the &#34;user defined building&#34; (I do not exactly know
        how it is called in english), you will see some additional program
        calls.</para>

        <para>To build the gui, you have to install Qt2.3 which includes some
        additional programs within a bin-folder, automatically installed. Set
        the environment variable &#34;QTDIR&#34; to the folder you have
        installed Qt into (not to the bin-folder as you may see from the calls
        within the project). This should let MSVC++ build the moc*-files
        first.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Netconvert</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Windows</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>The application hangs after a while (few memory consumption,
        most of the system time)</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>When I start the SUMO-NETCONEVERT
        with large networks, the system hangs after a while. The program uses
        most of the system time, but when I look into the task manager almost
        no memory is used.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> You are propably running a program
        compiled in the debug-mode. This yields in at least the triple of
        normal memory usage and your system hangs. Try to use the normal
        version, build in Release-mode.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Simulation</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Vehicles</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>No vehicle appears</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>I have build the network and
        routes like described, but no vehicle can be seen)</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> We encountered this problem under
        the following circumstances: As we imported a network where the
        maximum speed allowed on was given in km/h instead of the supposed
        m/s, no vehicle could be emitted due to a too large space needed for
        oncoming traffic. Check whether your network description also defines
        speed in km/h. If so, use the SUMO-NETCONVERT - switch
        &#34;speed-in-km&#34; to recompute the speed limits. If this does not
        help, contact us.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Visualisation</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Windows</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Display flickers in the area of the mouse pointer</title>

        <para><emphasis>Question: </emphasis>Why is the view around the mouse
        pointer distorted?</para>

        <para><emphasis>Answer:</emphasis> Newer Windows-Versions seem to
        cache the area under the mouse to apply the mouse shadow afterwards.
        To avoid this, go to your Systemmenu, then Mouse-&#62;Pointers and
        disable the mouse shadows. That&#39;s the only solution so far.
        (Origin: Till Oliver Knoll, via QT Interest List)</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>